and in today's video i want to sell you
something i'm not here to sell you an
nft project because i respect you all
way too much to do that and i'm also not
here to promote a specific project or a
coin because as we have all seen most of
them are scans and everything eventually
crashes what i want to sell you today is
a concept and learning this concept is
only going to cost you the time you
spend on it but learning this concept
might have a great return of investment
for your developer career and your
programming journey that concept is
blockchain development now many
developers shy away from learning about
blockchain development and i completely
understand why i have seen the news i am
aware of the scams i am aware of the
frauds and the crashes and i have lost
count how many times we have been
approached in this channel to promote
really scamming nfd projects i have seen
the nft influencers come work behind the
scenes but what if i told you that
behind all the frauds and scams and
crashes that make the news there is an
amazing technology powering it all
things and innovation that will blow up
your developer mind just because
technology can be used in a negative way
does not mean that we shouldn't even
learn how to use it let's look at the
internet for example really really awful
stuff goes on the internet much much
worse than scams and frauds but that did
not stop you and me from learning how to
make websites for example and i would
argue that is the same with the
blockchain this is why even if all the
projects that are going on right now all
the coins that you have heard of crash
and burn the ideas and the tech are here
to stay even governments from the us to
china and banks from everywhere in the
world are all looking into blockchain in
digital currencies so welcome to the
first of two videos where we are going
to become blockchain developers please
remember that if i mention any
cryptocurrency project that doesn't mean
that i'm telling you to buy it that
doesn't mean that i'm telling you that
it's a good investment i am aware that
everything can crash tomorrow everything
can go away except for the ideas and the
tech that we're going to discuss all
this information is for educational
purposes only do not put your hand and
money on any project without doing your
own research i am not telling you to buy
anything today just learn not buy learn
and thank you to all that note for
sponsoring this video if you don't know
what all that note is it's okay we're
going to talk about them later in the
video now let's get started as always we
have to start at the beginning and at
the beginning there was bitcoin the
easiest way that i found to explain
bitcoin to developers is to say that
bitcoin is just a distributed database
that means that it's a database that is
replicated across computers all around
the world and all these computers have
the exact same copy of the information
on that database the bitcoin database is
just a bunch of records of how much
bitcoins people have that's it if i send
you a bitcoin there is nothing actually
being sent the only thing that happens
is that on the database the owner of the
coins changes from my name to yours done
because databases are easy to modify and
everybody has a copy of this database
people could make changes to the
database into their records that are not
true to stop people from changing the
database in ways that are not honest the
creator of bitcoin chose a data
structure that makes our database append
only that means that people can only add
information to the database but they
cannot edit or delete anything from it
this data structure is a blockchain
which in developer speak you can imagine
that as a linked list a linked list is
one of the most basic data structures it
is composed of items also called nodes
and nodes have two parts one is the data
inside of the node and the other one is
a reference to the next item on the list
in the bitcoin world a note of this
linked list are called blocks like block
chain and the things inside of those
blocks are records of the transactions
of the bitcoins changing hands that's it
for a deeper explanation into blockchain
please watch these two videos after you
finish watching this one in these two
videos we go into much much more detail
about blockchains and who can modify
them so to recap bitcoin is a
distributed database the data structure
of this database is a linked list and
the nodes of this linked list hold data
about who has how many coins and every
new node in this linked list every new
block in this blockchain creates a state
transition that updates the database
done bitcoin from the beginning was
created to be internet money something
to make payments with a crypto currency
nothing else and nothing more but thanks
to bitcoin many people fell in love with
the concept of having a distributed
public and append only database and they
felt that this idea not only could be
used to keeping track of how much money
people have it could also be used to
keep track of all the values any value
they also believe that it should be
programmable that means they believe
that developers should be able to run
code on top of it this means that they
took the ideas from a public distributed
database and they transform it into a
public distributed computer now this is
when ethereum comes in
ethereum is not a cryptocurrency
ethereum is a public distributed
computer the ethereum computer has a
state which is what holds all the data
think of it like a ram random access
memory in a normal computer the ethereum
state can hold any kind of variable with
data types like booleans strings arrays
maps among many others this state is
replicated across thousands and
thousands of nodes on the ethereum
network and just like bitcoin ethereum
uses the blockchain data structure to
change state each new block in the
ethereum blockchain changes the state of
the computer making a variable go from
true to false or adding or removing
items from an array for example but who
is the one adding and removing items
from an array who is the one changing
variables from true to false are humans
doing that
no
unlike bitcoin where humans are the ones
that trigger a state transition when
they send coins to each other ethereum
allows its state to be changed not only
by humans but by code there are two
kinds of types of accounts in ethereum
one is called an externally owned
account and this is an account owned and
controlled by a human the other type of
account is called a contract account and
this is an account controlled by code
and this is when finally we as
developers have something to do using a
contract account the ones controlled by
code we can use this distributed global
computer to deploy our code hold the
values of our variables and run our
functions ethereum is basically a state
machine and we can use our code to
modify and create a data on this state
and that state is replicated across all
the nodes in the network all around the
world now tell me this doesn't sound
cool
and i know that now you have developer
questions such as for example what
language does this computer understand
where does the code actually run and who
runs the code when we write the code for
a contract account what we are doing is
we are writing a smart contract when you
write a smart contract for ethereum you
can do so in a variety of language but
chances are you're going to be doing
that in a programming language called
solidity solidity is a programming
language that you will be able to read
write and understand in less than 10
minutes if you know any other
programming language it's super simple
and as a spoiler that's exactly what
we're going to be doing on the next
video if you like the idea of writing
our first smart contract then please
leave a like and subscribe to the
channel so i can make the video quicker
like and subscribe it's just two clicks
is free for you but it helps me a lot
after we write our smart contract in
solidity what we do is we compile that
smart contract to byte code this byte
code will run inside of something called
the ethereum virtual machine or evm if
you are familiar with the java virtual
machine jvm then understand that evm
will be super easy for you the evm is
running on each node of the ethereum
network all these nodes are running the
evm all at once and if somebody calls
the code in our smart contract the node
will run our code and verify it all
together like a global computer the evm
is necessary for compatibility reasons
if we didn't have the evm then
developers would have to compile the
smart contracts for all different
platforms instead our smart contract
code can run on any node on any
operative system as long as it has the
evm so to recap ethereum really is a
globally distributed computer that can
hold our state run our functions and
keep track of our data just like a ram
would do and this computer also has a
virtual machine that is running on every
node in the network and we can write
code for it
the kinds of applications that this
allows us to write are applications that
require a high level of trust
transparency and verifiability after our
smart contract is uploaded to the
ethereum blockchain no one can change it
anymore and now i'm sure you have the
question that i had when i was learning
about all this the question is if
ethereum is a globally distributed
computer with an amazing virtual machine
what is ethereum doing in the
cryptocurrency exchanges if we buy
ethereum which again i'm not telling you
to but if we buy ethereum what are we
actually buying the evm and solidity
allow us to do things like for example a
for loop that means that in theory a
developer can write a program that runs
forever that uses infinite resources
bringing the network down
this could be done on purpose or by
accident but nevertheless is something
to protect against since the network is
running everybody's code for this reason
if we want to run our code in the
ethereum network the evm will charge you
a fee for the computational operations
that your contract needs to run this fee
is called gas and like a car needs gas
your smart contracts your code also
needs gas to be able to run now
different operations have different
prices in the evm for the add operation
the evm will charge you three gas units
and for the divide or multiple
operations you will have to pay five for
example the smart contract is going to
run for as long as there is gas on the
tank so if somebody rides a for loop
that runs forever it's actually not
going to run forever because the gas of
the contract is going to run out
to buy gas to run our contracts is when
we need to use the cryptocurrency called
ether and that is the one that you and
me can buy on the exchange because of
this gas idea is why the evm is known as
a quasi turing complete it's turning
complete but it won't run infinitely
because it will stop the moment the gas
runs out now i think that this gas idea
is a very good way of stopping bad code
from running forever and killing the
network but it's also when the problems
with ethereum start gas
fees in the past when many people used
the ethereum network at the same time
and they wanted to interact with
contracts the gas fees skyrocketed for
example when a super hyped nft project
was launched the network was so
congested that a user had to pay
3850 dollars on gas fees to buy a
275 dollar nft now i know this isn't
good news for you if you were thinking
of building an application for the
ethereum blockchain no user is going to
pay thousands of dollars to interact
with our code the ethereum team is aware
of this and they are solving the problem
but also are many other things projects
like clayton polygon avalanche moonbin
phantom edmonds among many
many others have been created to solve
the problems that ethereum has one way
or the other they all have their own
blockchains different networks different
parameters different ways of doing
things but the good news for developers
is that they share one thing in common
and that is the evm because the evm is
such a cool idea and because there is
already a lot of code written for the
evm all the projects i just mentioned
brought the evm to their blockchains so
developers can easily move their code to
the blockchain that has less gas fees
and faster confirmation types the future
in my opinion is multi-chain and we as
developers need to be able to talk to a
multiple amount of blockchains maybe a
government blockchain a bank blockchain
a public blockchain we should not marry
a specific platform or blockchain we
should be able to talk to them all
and this is when the sponsor of this
video comes in i have never taken any
sponsorship from any crypto project
because i love you all too much to sell
you an nft now all that note is not an
nft they are not selling a coin they
actually selling you nothing their
product is for free all that note is
developer infrastructure for the
blockchain as you saw before there are
many many blockchains and we as
developers need to be able to talk to
them all which means that we have to run
a node in our computer for every
blockchain that we want to interact with
or we can use all that no all that node
is an api that connects you to a
multiple amount of blockchains without
downloading anything only by using a url
you can interact with all the networks i
mentioned before they also support other
blockchains like solana cello near
cosmog agorik among many others and
they're adding networks to their
platform constantly the best thing of
all is that to interact with all of them
all you have to do is go to all that
note and get a free account which is
something that you can do right now in
the next video of this series we are
going to write our own smart contract
for a fundraising application like
kickstarter or what is but on the
blockchain and we are going to use all
that note to deploy our code to multiple
chains and that's it for this video
thank you so much for watching as always
if you like this content if you want to
support the channel consider leaving a
like and subscribing let me know what do
you think on the comments of this video
i'm going to be looking at them right
now thank you as always for watching and
stay happy stay free eat kimchi amazonia
salad hey yo see you on the next one bye